A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Program Action Index Cards, Accession 2017:064 FA1319
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Program Action Index Cards, Accession 2017:064
1936-1987
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA1319
7.6 Cubic Feet 23 8x5 Card File Boxes (Short)
Arrangement
The Ford Foundation Program Action Index Cards are divided into two series: 1. Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants 2. Program Action Index Cards - Field Office Grants.
Both series are arranged by Program Action (PA) number (loosely chronological by year). Gaps between PA numbers appear in both series.
Each Ford Foundation Grant and the corresponding Grant File is identified by a unique Program Action (PA) number. PA numbers begin with the year a grant was made (2-digits), followed by a sequential number within that year (4-digits).
For example: PA 55-0123 was the 123rd grant made in the year 1955. PA numbers are often typed or handwritten on Ford documents in the following format: 55-123 (year)-(####). However, the Ford Foundation's grants database (LINKS) uses an 8-digit format for PA numbers: 05500123 (0YY#####).
Beginning in the 1970s the 4th digit in the 8-digit PA number was used to encode at least three different types of Ford grants:
1. 0YY5#### = Delegated Authority Grants (DAG) / Delegated Authority Projects (DAP)
2. 0YY6#### = Grants to Individuals
3. 0YY9#### = Foundation Administered Projects (FAP)
Related Materials
Program Action Index Cards refer to microfilmed grants from the Ford Foundation's New York Office and Field Offices. The microfilm is held in the following collections:
FA732A Ford Foundation records, Grants, A-B
FA732B Ford Foundation records, Grants, C-D
FA732D Ford Foundation records, Grants, H-K
FA732E Ford Foundation records, Grants, L-N
FA732F Ford Foundation records, Grants, O-R
FA732G Ford Foundation records, Grants, S-Thel
FA732H Ford Foundation records, Grants, Them-Tw
FA732I Ford Foundation records, Grants, U-Z
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas.
During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2017 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as Accession 2017:064.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains Ford Foundation Program Action Index Cards/Microfilm Tracking Cards created and maintained by Ford Foundation's records management program. The cards tracked the microfilming process of the Ford Foundation's New York Office and Field Offices' grant materials. The cards served as a checklist for records management tasks and they include some/all of the following information: Program Area Number, Microfilm Reel Number, Date Transferred to Archives, Main File/Attachments Located, Grant Closing Date, Grant Processed, Grants Accounting File Processed, Microfilm Box Number, Date Box Sent, Date Film Returned, Program Area Acronym, Film inspection Date, and Grant Destruction Authorized.
- Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants, 1936-1987; 1
  - Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants - 36-234 - 55-235, 1936-1955 (Box 1)
  - Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants - 56-1 - 56-999, 1956 (Box 2)
  - Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants - 56-1000 - 58-404, 1956-1958 (Box 3)
  - Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants - 59-2 - 60-476, 1959-1960 (Box 4)
  - Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants - 61-1 - 62-523, 1961-1962 (Box 5)
  - Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants - 639-0001 - 64-300, 1963-1964 (Box 6)
  - Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants - 64-301 - 66-300, 1964-1966 (Box 7)
  - Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants - 66-301 - 68-199, 1966-1968 (Box 8)
  - Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants - 68-200 - 69-299, 1968-1969 (Box 9)
  - Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants - 69-301 - 70-984, 1969-1970 (Box 10)
  - Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants - 719-0001 - 72-985, 1971-1972 (Box 11)
  - Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants - 739-0001 - 73-985, 1973 (Box 12)
  - Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants - 749-0001 - 750-0299, 1974-1975 (Box 13)
  - Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants - 75-301 - 769-0827, 1975-1976 (Box 14)
  - Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants - 775-011 - 785-0299, 1977-1978 (Box 15)
  - Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants - 78-300 - 79-499, 1978-1979 (Box 16)
  - Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants - 79-500 - 805-903, 1979-1980 (Box 17)
  - Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants - 815-010 - 81-1076, 1981 (Box 18)
  - Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants - 820-011 - 825-1233, 1982 (Box 19)
  - Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants - 835-0011 - 835-1098, 1983 (Box 20)
  - Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants - 845-0010 - 845-0967, 1984 (Box 21)
  - Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants - 855-0012 - 855-1061, 1985 (Box 21)
  - Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants - 865-0022 - 865-1075, 1986 (Box 21)
  - Program Action Index Cards - New York Office Grants - 875-0058 - 870-832, 1987 (Box 21)
- Program Action Index Cards - Field Office Grants, 1950-1984; 2
  - Program Action Index Cards - Field Office Grants - 50-3 - 65-358, 1950-1965 (Box 22)
    Scope and Contents
    Field office locations include: India; Islamabad, Pakistan; Lagos, Nigeria; Cairo, Egypt; Rio, Brazil; Thailand; Santiago, Chile; Bogota, Colombia; Jakarta, Indonesia; Buenos Aires, Argentina; Mexico; Riyadh, Saudi Arabia; Manila, Philippines; Peru
  - Program Action Index Cards - Field Office Grants - 66-86 - 71-577, 1966-1971 (Box 22)
    Field office locations include: India; Islamabad, Pakistan; Lagos, Nigeria; Cairo, Egypt; Rio, Brazil; Thailand; Santiago, Chile; Bogota, Colombia; Jakarta, Indonesia; Buenos Aires, Argentina; Mexico; Riyadh, Saudi Arabia; Manila, Philippines; Lima, Peru; Paris, France
  - Program Action Index Cards - Field Office Grants - 72-1 - 76-825, 1972-1976 (Box 23)
  - Program Action Index Cards - Field Office Grants - 77-11 - 84-417, 1977-1984 (Box 23)